So I've been thinking about the difference between
لطالما فكرت في الفرق بين
the résumé virtues and the eulogy virtues.
فضائل السيرة الذاتية وفضائل خطاب التأبين.
The résumé virtues are the ones you put on your résumé,
فضائل السيرة الذاتية هي التي تضعها في سيرتك الذاتية،
which are the skills you bring to the marketplace.
وهي المهارات التي تأتي بها إلى سوق الشغل.
The eulogy virtues are the ones
وفضائل خطاب التأبين هي تلك
that get mentioned in the eulogy,
التي تذكر في مراسم التأبين،
which are deeper: who are you, in your depth,
وتتميزبالعمق: من تكون، في عمقك،
what is the nature of your relationships,
ماهي طبيعة علاقاتك،
are you bold, loving, dependable, consistency?
هل أنت جريء، محبوب، جدير بالثقة، مستقيم؟
And most of us, including me, would say
ومعظمنا، وأنا منهم، سيقول
that the eulogy virtues are the more important of the virtues.
أن فضائل خطاب التأبين هي أهم الفضائل.
But at least in my case, are they the ones that
على الأقل فيما يخصني، هل هي الخصائص
I think about the most? And the answer is no.
التي أفكر بها بشكل أكبر؟ الجواب هو لا.
So I've been thinking about that problem,
لذا فقد ظلت أفكر في هذا الموضوع،
and a thinker who has helped me think about it
والمفكر الذي ساعدني في التفكير فيه
is a guy named Joseph Soloveitchik, who was a rabbi
هو شخص يدعى جوزيف سولوفيتشيك، وهو حاخام
who wrote a book called "The Lonely Man Of Faith" in 1965.
والذي كتب كتاب "رجل الإيمان الوحيد" سنة 1965.
Soloveitchik said there are two sides of our natures,
يقول سولوفيتشيك أن لدينا جانبين من طبيعتنا،
which he called Adam I and Adam II.
والذين سماهما آدام I وآدم II.
Adam I is the worldly, ambitious,
آدام الأول: دنيوي، طموح،
external side of our nature.
وهو الجانب الخارجي لطبيعتنا،
He wants to build, create, create companies,
يريد أن يبني، أن ييبدع، أن ينشئ شركات،
create innovation.
أن يبتكر.
Adam II is the humble side of our nature.
آدم الثاني هو الجانب المتواضع من طبيعتنا.
Adam II wants not only to do good but to be good,
آدم الثاني لا يريد أن يفعل الخير فقط، بل أن يكون خيِّرا،
to live in a way internally
أن يعيش بطريقة
that honors God, creation and our possibilities.
يقدس فيها الله بداخله، ويجل الخلق وجميع إمكانياتنا.
Adam I wants to conquer the world.
آدم الأول يريد أن يفتح العالم.
Adam II wants to hear a calling and obey the world.
آدم الثاني يريد أن يسمع النداء ويرضي العالم.
Adam I savors accomplishment.
آدم الأول يتذوق الإنجازات.
Adam II savors inner consistency and strength.
آدم الثاني يتذوق الاستقامة والقوة.
Adam I asks how things work.
آدم الأول يسأل كيف تعمل الأشياء.
Adam II asks why we're here.
آدم الثاني يسأل لماذا نحن هنا.
Adam I's motto is "success."
شعار آدم الأول هو "النجاح".
Adam II's motto is "love, redemption and return."
شعار آدم الثاني هو "الحب والخلاص والعودة".
And Soloveitchik argued that these two sides
ويجادل سولوفيتشيك أن هاذين الجانبين
of our nature are at war with each other.
من طبيعتنا في حالة حرب بينهما.
We live in perpetual self-confrontation
فنحن نعيش في مواجهة دائمة مع أنفسنا
between the external success and the internal value.
بين النجاح الخارجي والقيمة الداخلية.
And the tricky thing, I'd say, about these
والجزء المخادع، عليَّ أن أقول،
two sides of our nature is they work
فيما يخص جزأي طبيعتنا هو أنهما يعملان
by different logics.
تبعا لمنطقين مختلفين.
The external logic is an economic logic:
المنطق الخارجي هو منطق اقتصادي:
input leads to output, risk leads to reward.
المخاطرة تؤدي إلى الربح.
The internal side of our nature
الجانب الداخلي من طبيعتنا
is a moral logic and often an inverse logic.
هو منطق أخلاقي وغالبا منطق عكسي.
You have to give to receive.
عليك أن تعطي لكي تأخذ.
You have to surrender to something outside yourself
عليك أن تتنازل عن شيء خارجي
to gain strength within yourself.
لكي تكتسب قوة داخلك.
You have to conquer the desire to get what you want.
عليك أن تقهر الرغبة لتحصل على ما تريد.
In order to fulfill yourself, you have to forget yourself.
لكي ترضي نفسك، عليك أن تنسى نفسك.
In order to find yourself, you have to lose yourself.
لكي تجد نفسك، عليك أن تُضيع نفسك.
We happen to live in a society that favors Adam I,
يصدف أننا نعيش في مجتمع يفضل آدم الأول.
and often neglects Adam II.
وغالبا ما يتجاهل آدم الثاني.
And the problem is, that turns you into a shrewd animal
والمشكل أن هذا، يحولك إلى حيوان شره،
who treats life as a game,
يتعامل مع الحياة كلعبة،
and you become a cold, calculating creature
فتصبح مخلوقا باردا ماكرا،
who slips into a sort of mediocrity
فتنزلق في نوع من الوضاعة،
where you realize there's a difference
حيث تدرك أن ثمة فرقا بين
between your desired self and your actual self.
النفس التي ترغب فيها ونفسك الحقيقية.
You're not earning the sort of eulogy you want,
فأنت لا تكتسب الإطراء الذي تريده،
you hope someone will give to you.
بل تتمنى أن يعطيك أحدهم إياه.
You don't have the depth of conviction.
ليست لديك القناعة الراسخة.
You don't have an emotional sonorousness.
ليست لك عاطفة جهورية.
You don't have commitment to tasks
ليس لديك ذلك الالتزام بالمهام
that would take more than a lifetime to commit.
التي تتطلب وقتا طويلا لكي تتعهد بها.
I was reminded of a common response through history
تذكرت طريقة شائعة للتجاوب مع هذا خلال التاريخ
of how you build a solid Adam II,
كيف لك أن تبني نسخة قوية من آدم الثاني،
how you build a depth of character.
كيف لك أن تبني صفة العمق فيك.
Through history, people have gone back
عبر التاريخ، كان الناس يعودون
into their own pasts,
إلى ماضيهم الخاص،
sometimes to a precious time in their life,
في بعض الأحيان إلى وقت غال من حياتهم،
to their childhood,
إلى طفولتهم،
and often, the mind gravitates in the past
وغالبا ما ينجذب عقلهم في الماضي
to a moment of shame,
إلى لحظة خزي ما،
some sin committed, some act of selfishness,
إلى ذنب اقترفوه، أو فعل أناني،
an act of omission, of shallowness,
حالة غفلة، حالة سطحية،
the sin of anger, the sin of self-pity,
ذنب الغضب، ذنب احتقار الذات،
trying to be a people-pleaser, a lack of courage.
في محاولة لإرضاء الناس، وانعدام الشجاعة.
Adam I is built by building on your strengths.
يُبنى آدم الأول ببناء نقاط قوتك.
Adam II is built by fighting your weaknesses.
يُبنى آدم الثاني بمواجهة نقاط ضعفك.
You go into yourself, you find the sin
تبحث بداخلك، وتجد ذلك الذنب
which you've committed over and again through your life,
الذي اقترفته مرارا وتكرارا طيلة حياتك،
your signature sin
الذنب الأساسي
out of which the others emerge,
الذي تنبثق منه الخطايا الأخرى،
and you fight that sin and you wrestle with that sin,
فتحارب ذلك الذنب، وتصارع ذلك الذنب،
and out of that wrestling, that suffering,
ومن خلال هذا الكفاح، هذه المعاناة،
then a depth of character is constructed.
تُبنى صفة العمق فيك.
And we're often not taught to recognize
لكننا غالبا لم نتعلم كيف ندرك
the sin in ourselves,
وجود الذنب بأنفسنا،
in that we're not taught in this culture
لذا فلم نتعلم في ثقافتنا هذه
how to wrestle with it,
كيف نصارعه،
how to confront it, and how to combat it.
وكيف نواجهه، وكيف نحاربه.
We live in a culture with an Adam I mentality
نعيش في ثقافة بعقلية آدم الأول
where we're inarticulate about Adam II.
غير صرحاء بشأن آدم الثاني.
Finally, Reinhold Niebuhr
وفي الأخير، فقد لخص رينهولد بينور
summed up the confrontation, the fully lived
المواجهة، الحياة الكاملة
Adam I and Adam II life, this way:
لآدم الأول وآدم الثاني، كما يلي:
"Nothing that is worth doing can be achieved in our lifetime;
ما من شيء يستحق القيام به، يمكن أن تحققه خلال حياتك
therefore we must be saved by hope.
وبالتالي علينا أن ننقذ أنفسنا بالأمل.
Nothing which is true or beautiful or good makes
ما من شيء يحمل صفات الحقيقة والجمال والخير، يبدو
complete sense in any immediate context of history;
منطقيا خلال النطاق التاريخي الذي حدث فيه؛
therefore we must be saved by faith.
لذلك علينا أن نتحلى بالإيمان.
Nothing we do, however virtuous, can be accomplished alone;
ما من شيء نقوم به، وإن كان فاضلا، يمكن تحقيقه بمفردنا؛
therefore we must be saved by love.
لذا فعلينا أن نتحلى بالحب.
No virtuous act is quite as virtuous
ليس هناك فعل فاضل، بالنسبة
from the standpoint of our friend or foe as from our own standpoint.
لصديق أو عدو بقدرما يكون فاضلا بالنسبة لك أنت.
Therefore we must be saved by that final form of love,
لذا فعلينا أن نتحلى بأقصى درجات الحب،
which is forgiveness.”
والتي هي المغفرة"
Thanks.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)